<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of Virginia and Mary-land with the commodities therein, which in part the author saw, the rest he had from knowing and credible persons in the moneths of February, March, April and May / by Nathaniel Shrigley.</title>
            <author>Shrigley, Nathaniel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60162</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3697</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11328</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11910464</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11910464</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50790</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60162)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50790)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 512:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of Virginia and Mary-land with the commodities therein, which in part the author saw, the rest he had from knowing and credible persons in the moneths of February, March, April and May / by Nathaniel Shrigley.</title>
                  <author>Shrigley, Nathaniel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Milbourn for Thomas Hodson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1669]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Virginia --  Description and travel.</term>
               <term>Maryland --  Description and travel.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50790:1"/>
            <p>A TRUE RELATION OF VIRGINIA AND Mary-Land; With the Commodities therein, which in part the Author ſaw; the reſt he had from know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Credible perſons in the Moneths of <hi>February, March, April</hi> and <hi>May:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Nathaniel Shrigley,</hi> Anno. 1669.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Allowance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Milbourn</hi> for <hi>Thomas Hodſon</hi> Book-binder, Living the next door to the Signe of the <hi>Blew-Boar</hi> in <hi>Redcroſs Street.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50790:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50790:2"/>
            <head>A TRUE RELATION OF <hi>VIRGINIA</hi> and <hi>MARY-LAND,</hi> With the Commodities therein, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>IMprimis,</hi> the <hi>Capes</hi> are in the Latitude of 37 Longitude of 302. from whence a Large <hi>Bay</hi> called <hi>Cheſebeack Bay</hi> flowes about ſeaven Leagues broad <hi>N.</hi> by <hi>E.</hi> betwixt three and four degrees in length; then it bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches it ſelf into many ſmall Rivers: the depth of the <hi>Bay</hi> is ſeaven, ten, twelve, or fourteen Fatham; it hath ſeveral ſmall Iſlands in it. Out of which <hi>Bay</hi> on the <hi>Eaſt</hi> ſide, theſe are the principal Rivers, <hi>Anameſax, Ockahanock, Nautecocke,</hi> little <hi>Choptauke,</hi> great <hi>Choptauke,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:50790:3"/> St. <hi>Michaels, Wy River, Cheſter, Sacifrax River.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the <hi>Weſt</hi> ſide theſe are the principle Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, <hi>Elizabeth, Nanſemum, James, Back, Yorke, Rapahanock, Petomock, Patuxon, Soueth, Severn, Gunpowder</hi> River, <hi>Patapſco;</hi> from which River the <hi>Bay</hi> draws ſtraiter, and devides it ſelf into many leſſer Rivers.</p>
            <p>Out of which <hi>Bay</hi> and Rivers, there are branched many Navigable Rivers and Creeks, the which no Ten men in the Land are able to nominate.</p>
            <p>The Shore on the <hi>Eaſt</hi> from the <hi>Bay</hi> to the Ocean, is but about twenty miles broad.</p>
            <p>The Rivers on the <hi>Weſt</hi> of the <hi>Bay</hi> are Navigable, ſome 40. ſome 50. ſome 100. ſome 200. ſome 300. miles; which Bay, Rivers and Creeks are plentiful of Fowle from <hi>September</hi> till <hi>March,</hi> of all ſorts, as Swans, Geeſe, Brants, Ducks, Widgeon, Teale, with many other ſorts too tedious to relate, ſome of which tarry with them all <hi>Summer:</hi> And Fiſh multitudes, as Porpoſſes, Grampaſes, Herring-Hoggs, Drums, Sheepſheads, Baſs, Mullets, Pearch, Sturgeon, Eales, Salmon, Trouts, Thornbacks, Garrs, Cats, Oyſters, Crabs, Turtles, with many more too tedious to relate.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:50790:3"/>
            <p>The Cattle naturally of the Country, are Bucks, Does, Staggs, Hindes, Hares, Ratoons, Poſſums, Beavers, Otters, Lyons, Bears, Wolves, Panthers, Leopards, Foxes, Wilde Cats, with many more.</p>
            <p>Fowle naturally to the Land are Eagles, Hawks, Vultures, Cranes, Crows, Turkies, Partridges, Pidgions, Larks, Red-birds, the Baltenore bird, being black and yellow, blew Birds, mocking Birds, Woodpickers, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſorts more.</p>
            <p>Engliſh Cattle; plenty of Cows, Bulls, Oxen, Sheep, Goats, Swine, Horſes, and all manner of Engliſh Poultrey.</p>
            <div type="list_of_trees">
               <p>The Country is naturally full of <hi>Vines, Fruit Trees,</hi> and <hi>Timber,</hi> As,
<list>
                     <item>F. <hi>Mulberries.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>F. <hi>Plumbs.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>F. <hi>Peſimmons.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>T. <hi>Aſh.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Holly.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>T. <hi>Elder.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>F. <hi>Cherries</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>M. <hi>Beach.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Locuſt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>N <hi>Haſle.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:50790:4"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>T. <hi>Cheſnut.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>T. <hi>Poplar.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>T. <hi>Pine.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Oaks. A. T.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>White.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Red.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Black.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Saſifrax.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>T. <hi>Ceder.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cheſnut.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Spaniſh.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>T. <hi>Cypreſs.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Syccamore.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>T. <hi>Wallnut.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Gum Trees being cut, runns Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome,</hi> with many others</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pekickery.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Saſiperella.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Trees marked <hi>F.</hi> are fruite, <hi>M.</hi> are Maſs or feeding for Swine, T. timber or plank, A. Acorns, N. Nutts, with Grape-Vines climbing up the trees very fruitfull; and Hops alſo in the Woods; multitudes of Rasberies, Strawberies, Barberies, Cranberies, with infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite of all ſorts of Hearbs; the beſt Garden in <hi>England</hi> affords not better.</p>
               <p>In Orchards all ſorts of Apple-Trees, Pear-Trees, Quince, Peach, Apricocks, Cherries, Figg-Trees, and Vines; Gardens as good as <hi>England</hi> affords for flowers, hearbs and roots of all ſorts; with Colworts, Muſmillions, Cue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbers, Wate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>millions, May-cocks, Hornes, Peſhaues, Roſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>Trees, ſweet-Bryers, and many things more.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:50790:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>There is a Root common in the Woods called <hi>Tuckaho,</hi> the Natives eat it for bread; our Swine eat it; with Acorns and Nuts of all ſorts, they are Fat; and is the ſweeteſt Bacon that ever man taſted.</p>
               <p>The planters feed not their Swine nor Cattle, but kill them fat out of the Woods.</p>
               <p>There is Fullers-Earth, Marle, Salt-peter, Iron, Stone, Lead, Tin and Silver Oar.</p>
               <p>There is plenty of Engliſh graine, as Wheat, Barley, Beanes, Peas and Oats.</p>
               <p>The ground is very fruitful, and produceth plentiful Crops with great ſpeed, what ever is planted or Sown; as for example, one careful laborious man will plant, tend, and get in 50. barrels of Indian Wheat, without the help of Man, Horſe or Oxe; each barrel is five Engliſh buſhels. And if the ſtone or ſee of any fruit be ſown, it will bear the third year without graft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; each Planter makes great Crops of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco; the <hi>Weſtern</hi> limits of the Land are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known In <hi>Mary-Land;</hi> their Religion is free to all that profeſs to believe in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
